Guide to the Ronald Bay Furry papers, circa 1957-1997.
Furry, Ronald Bay papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ronald Bay Furry papers, circa 1957-1997.
21-11-4261
Furry, Ronald Bay.
3.5 cubic feet.
Correspondence, research materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists of historical documents relating to Ronald Furry's 42 years on the Cornell faculty in the teaching, research and Extension programs, including course material, research material and items on the Layer Fund.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Following 42 years of service at Cornell University, Ronald Bay Furry (b. October 22, 1931), Professor of Agricultural and Biological Engineering, retired August 30, 1995 and was granted Emeritus status. Furry received his BS (1953, with Distinction) and MS (1955) degrees from Cornell University, and his PhD (1965) from Iowa State University.
During his tenure at Cornell, Furry participated in all three mission functions of the Department: Teaching, Research and Extension, and served as its Chairman during 1990-94. His principal research interests centered on postharvest controlled atmosphere environments for agricultural materials, while his Extension efforts included responsibility for the dairy structures program for New York State, as well as the Extension Plan Service. He enjoyed teaching immensely, and taught undergraduate and graduate courses ranging from computer programming and computer graphics through similitude methodology. His publications include fifteen sole-author, eighteen principal-author, and seventeen contributing-author papers; sixty engineering bulletins, mostly sole-authored; four manuals and guides; one book chapter; one-hundred-seventy articles; thirty-two structural design plan sets; and seventy-eight serial newsletters. In addition, he developed several mainframe and microcomputer engineering design application packages which he utilized extensively in his teaching program. He also served the Department as Coordinator of Research and Graduate Faculty Representative, participated in a wide variety of College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, College of Engineering and University responsibilities, including the University Senate and the Faculty Council of Representatives, and established and conducted the Department’s undergraduate recruitment program from 1974 to his retirement. In 2007, he wrote A Pioneering Department: Evolution from Rural Engineering to Biological and Environmental Engineering at Cornell University, 1907-2007, that traces the evolution of the Department of Biological and Environmental Engineering (BEE) at Cornell over its first 100 years.
Furry received early recognition as a National Science Foundation Science Faculty Fellow, and a Ford Foundation Prospective Teacher in Engineering. In 1992, he was elected a Fellow of the American Society of Agricultural Engineers (ASAE, now ASABE). He was the recipient of several blue ribbon awards from ASAE. In 1993, the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) awarded him its Centennial Certificate for Exceptional Contributions to ASEE and the Profession of Engineering. He also served as Chairman of the Biological and Agricultural Engineering Division of ASEE.
Furry is a member of Phi Kappa Phi, Sigma Xi, a charter member of Gamma Sigma Delta at Cornell, and a member of Alpha Zeta (AZ), where he served on the Board of Directors for several decades; he was the AZ Board’s Facility Program Chairman during the construction of the fraternity‘s new house which was dedicated in 1993. He was a charter member (1962) of the Ithaca Sertoma Club, and an early member (1954) and active participant of the Cornell Federal Credit Union (CFCU), now CFCU Community Credit Union. He served on the Credit Union’s Board of Directors for eleven years, and was its Chairman for four years. He was a Distinguished Military Graduate of AFROTC at Cornell University and reached the rank of 1st Lt. in the USAFRes.
Ron is married to Lois Anne McClure (Ithaca College 1955). They have three children - Suzanne Lynne Furry-Irish, married to L. Paul Irish; Kenneth B. Furry; and Donna Wynne Furry Tongue, married to Donald V. Tongue. The Furrys have five grandchildren and two great-grandchildren. His sister, Joanne Louise Furry, was married to his best friend and fellow Cornell classmate David P. Dirksen.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of historical documents relating to Ronald Furry's 42 years on the Cornell faculty in the teaching, research and Extension programs, including course material, research material and items on the Layer Fund, agricultural, biological, and environmental engineering.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Furry, Ronald Bay, 1931-
Subjects:
Agricultural Engineering.; Bioengineering.; Environmental engineering.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Personal files, 1987-1993
  - "Reorganization (Petronius arbiter)", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    A variety of humorous quotations, jokes and cartoons. Includes floppy disk labeled "Boyd's Quotes!"
  - "Boyd's Quotes!", Undated; FD-370 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Murphy's law, quotes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Humorous quotations about Murphy's Law.
  - "Chinese proverb", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Chinese proverb and calligraphy.
  - "Translation Test", 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Copies of a joke test and one other humorous test.
  - "Far Above Cayuga's Waters-Sokol", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Explanation of origins of Cornell's Alma Mater.
- Departmental files, 1914-1997
  Series includes correspondence.
  - Professional development, 1914-1992
    - Resumes, 1982-1992, 2018 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biographical info, 1957-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ASAE Nomination & C.V., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Publications authored by R. Furry, 1956-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
      Includes papers presented to colloquiums, professional associations, agricultural extension bulletins, Farm Research
    - Farm Research pub., 1956-01 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes photo of Furry at Cornell Orchards.
    - Geheminis Sharpstein, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Seminar, includes transparencies.
    - Research pubs of agricultural historical interest, 1914-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes a variety agricultural bulletins and reprints of historic interest, eg, reprint of speech by Liberty Hyde Bailey, 1914.
  - Layer fund, 1975-1997
    - Recommendation of recipient forms, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Recipients data and list, 1981-1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - VHS Computer Magic: The World of Computer Imagery, Cinemagic Productions, Undated; V-9865 (Box 1)
      VHS, 58 Minutes, Produced by Colyer Dupont
    - Donors & acknowledgment letters, 1975-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Research, 1938-1987
    - "Pentairy-R.B. Furry 1959-1960", 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Includes photo negatives, photo R. Furry with model of Pentairy.
    - The Pentairy Visual Aids, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Includes B&W photos with close-up views of model Pentairy
    - Pentairy Design, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Includes Pentairy design notes, exhibit notes, newspaper clippings
    - Farm & Home Week (Critique), 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Includes exhibit critique, additional Pentairy design notes, cow cartoon
    - World Agriculture pub, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Page 21 photo of Plentairy exhibit in Cairo.
    - Miner Institute & agricultural Pubs, 1938-1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Sample of agriculture pubs with variety of dates. Includes sheet of slides from Oct. 1972 at Miner Institute.
    - Miner Waste, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Includes 3 sheets of slides of dairy related structures and 2 b&w photographs (size 8 x 11). Slides imprinted with the name W.W. Irish.
    - Miner Institute, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      3 sheets of dairy related slides at Miner Institute. A few with hand written labels.
- Instruction, 1957-1991
  - Courses, 1965-1991
    Arranged by course number.
    - ABEN 204: Recs (1), Spring 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - ABEN 204: Recs (2), Spring 1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - ABEN 204: Labs (1), Spring 1990 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - ABEN 204: Labs (2), Spring 1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - ABEN 204: #1 (1), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Includes floppy disk (unlabeled)
    - Untitled, Undated; FD-371 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - ABEN 204: #1 (2), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - ABEN 204: #1 (3), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - ABEN 204: #2 (1), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - ABEN 204: #2 (2), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - ABEN 204: #3 (1), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - ABEN 204: #3 (2), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - ABEN 204: #4, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - ABEN 204: TA orientation & staff meetings, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes 3 pages of photos of classroom set-up and blackboard notes.
    - ABEN 204: Lecture handouts, Spring 1990 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Organized by "week 1, week 2" etc.
    - ABEN 465: Drying #1 (1), 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Research articles dated over a range of years.
    - ABEN 465: Drying #1 (2), 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - ABEN 465: Drying #2 (1), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - ABEN 465: Drying #2 (2), Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Handwritten notes undated. Research articles from the mid-1960s.
    - ABEN 465: Drying #2 (3), 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Research articles.
    - ABEN 465: Dimensional Analysis (1), 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - ABEN 465: Dimensional Analysis (2), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - ABEN 465: Dimensional Analysis (3), 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - ABEN 465: Granular Flow Measure (1), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - ABEN 465: Granular Flow Measure (2), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - ABEN 465: Apple Storage (1), 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - ABEN 465: Apple Storage (2), 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - ABEN 465: Apple Storage (3), 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Includes photos of whiteboard notes
    - ABEN 465: Teaching Assistant (1), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - ABEN 465: Teaching Assistant (2), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - ABEN 465: Pump/Reservoir Simulation, 1973-1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Notes and research over a broad range of dates
    - ABEN 465: Agricultural Materials Handling Manual (1), 1981-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - ABEN 465: Agricultural Materials Handling Manual (2), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - ABEN 465: Agricultural Materials Handling Manual (3), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - ABEN 465: G Pump listing, Pump Reservoir System, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - ABEN 465: G pump, Auto, Grapher Differ, Source & Execs, AutoCAD-Orchard.dwg, 1987-12-06; FD-369 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      5" floppy disk
    - ABEN 465: Pump/Fan Laws, Pump Reservoir (1), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - ABEN 465: Pump/Fan Laws, Pump Reservoir (2), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Agriculture Engineering 501 Term Project, 1973-05 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Includes photographs of deposition patterns
    - ABEN 651: Similitude Methodology, 1966-1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Research articles from 1966-1974, some annotated by Furry.
    - AGR ENG 651, 1965-1979 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Includes published paper authored by Furry, handwritten notes and other research.
  - Supplemental teaching materials, 1957-1990
    - Conversion Tables, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - ABEN: Teaching Materials (1), 1964-1990 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Variety of materials including a USDA set of wheat samples, final exam for ABEN 465
    - ABEN: Teaching Materials (2), Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - ABEN: Teaching Materials (3), 1974-1990 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - ABEN: Teaching Materials (4), 1979-1994 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Dairy Structures Guide, 1957-04 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Slide Rule Use Instructions, Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
      A variety of guides for slide rules.
    - Alvin Precision Drawing Set, Undated; MU-1859 (Box 4)
      Set of metal drawing instruments in a hard blue cover.
    - Concise Conversion Tables, Circular Slide Rule, 1967; MU-1860 (Box 4)
      Plastic circular slide rule and paper instruction guide in a white plastic wallet, approx. 4" x 3"
    - Concise Conversion Tables, Circular Slide Rule, 1966; MU-1861 (Box 4)
      Plastic circular slide rule and paper instruction guide in a blue plastic wallet, approx. 4" x 3"
    - Book: "Fan Engineering", edited by Richard D. Madison, TJ960 F19 3rd ed., 1933 (Box 4)